Shavua Tov, today's דף daf is מה. Mem Hey. We pick up
at the bottom of מד עמוד ב Mem Dalet Amud Bet and
we're dealing with the debate here about of the various coinages of
different precious metals, particularly gold, silver, and copper, which
one is
sort of seen as the standard by which the others are defined
in terms of? So there's a debate about בית הלל Beit Hillel
and בית שמאי Beit Shammai that if you redeemed your מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni onto silver coins, can you now transfer those silver coins,
exchange them for gold coins, transfer the קדושה kedusha from the silver
to the gold, where בית שמאי Beit Shammai said that you could
not and בית הלל Beit Hillel said that you could. So the
question is what is that debate? So the גמרא Gemara first is
assuming that the debate is similar to the questions about רבי's Rebbi
two versions of the משנה, mishna, whether gold relative to silver is
considered a coin or not. If gold relative to silver is considered
a coin, then you can transfer מעשר שני Maaser Sheni to coin.
But if gold relative to silver is considered fruit, non-coin, you cannot
transfer מעשר שני Maaser Sheni from a coin to fruit. So בית
שמאי Beit Shammai who says you can transfer to gold does not
consider it to be coin relative to silver and בית הלל Beit
Hillel says that you do, that you can. Within that, there's a
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish whether
בית שמאי Beit Shammai would allow you to go straight from fruit
to gold coin. Would בית שמאי Beit Shammai say that gold coin
is never, never considered coin, it's always considered תרופיס, trovis, you know,
or would he just say no, only relative to silver? So that's
the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
within בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So we pick up מד עמוד ב
Mem Dalet Amud Bet and we pick up with the וחד
אמר. vachad amar. Let's just pick up from there, it's about one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven, nine lines from the bottom and
the line starts with the word טיבעא הוי. tivha havei. וחד אמר,
Vachad amar, the other one of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish says, אף הפירות על דינרים מחלוקת. af haperos al
dinarim machlokes. No, the debate would even be from fruit straight to
the gold coins, even that בית שמאי Beit Shammai would not allow.
Okay, because gold coins according to this version are not just not
coin relative to silver, they're not coin at all. ולמאן דאמר אף
הפירות על דינרים מחלוקת, Uliman damar af haperos al dinarim machlokes, according
to that version, אדמיפלגי בסלעים על דינרים, adimifligi bislayim al dinarim, so
why are they debating going from silver to gold? ליפלוג בהפירות על
דינרים. Liphlog behaperos al dinarim. Debate from going from fruit to gold,
that's a bigger חידוש chiddush that בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't consider
gold to be a coin at all even when you're going from
fruit to gold. It says no, איפלגו בהפירות על דינרים, ifligo behaperos
al dinarim, had they debated that case, הני מילי הפירות על דינרים,
hani mili haperos al dinarim, then that's the only case that בית
הלל Beit Hillel objects, because he says at least relative to fruit,
gold is considered a coin. אבל בסלעים על דינרים, Aval bislayim al
dinarim, but then I might have thought that when you go from
silver to gold, מודו ליה בית הלל לבית שמאי, modu leh Beit
Hillel l'Beit Shammai, maybe בית הלל Beit Hillel would agree that relative
to silver it's not a coin, דגבי כספא פירא הוי, dgabei kaspa
peira havei, that gold relative to silver is fruit, not a coin,
ולא מחללינן v'lo michalelinan and it would not work. קא משמע לן,
Kamashma lan, that you don't say that. Okay, so anyway so therefore
they're debating silver to gold, it's a bigger חידוש chiddush that even
relative to silver, בית הלל Beit Hillel considers gold to be a
coin. How would בית שמאי Beit Shammai treat gold relative to fruit?
That's not so clear, is he just objecting in the relative case,
relative to silver, or would he never really consider gold to be
a coin? Okay, so now we're going to try to figure out
which who says which of those two opinions in בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. It doesn't mean that you can't use it, but it means
that for הלכות, halachos, obviously practically it's used, but for הלכות halachos
that require currency, it's considered so rare that it's not considered currency.
Look, a thousand dollar bill is currency, right? Go try to use
it in the store. Okay. תסתיים Tistayem דרבי יוחנן הוא דאמר אין
מחללין. d'Rabbi Yochanan hu damar ain michalelin. Let's conclude that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is the one that says that according to בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, you can't even go from fruit to gold.
דאמר רבי יוחנן, Damar Rabbi Yochanan, top of מה עמוד א, Mem
Hey Amud Aleph, אסור להלוות דינר בדינר. asur lihalvos dinar bidinar. You
cannot borrow in דינרי dinarei to pay back in דינרי. dinarei. Now
that seems a little crazy, right? Why not? Okay, so exactly. So
the point is, and this involves what we discussed yesterday, that you
have to decide which of the currencies you're borrowing in is defined
as the currency to figure out the dollar value of what you
borrowed. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says let's see, דינר דמאי, dinar
d'mai, what type of דינר? dinar? אילימא דינר דכסף בדינר דכסף, Ilima
dinar dikeseph bdinar dikeseph, silver coins with silver coins? לגבי נפשיה מי
איכא למאן דאמר לאו טיבעא הוי? Legabei nafshai mi ika l'man damar
lav tivha havei? Who would ever say that silver relative to itself,
meaning when you're not dealing with another coin, another type of a
coin, you're just dealing in a world borrowing with silver and paying
back with silver, nobody would ever say that that is not considered
currency.
Okay, which is a little funny because yesterday we somewhat maybe raised
the possibility otherwise, but at least here within the בית הלל Beit
Hillel בית שמאי Beit Shammai debate, silver is clearly currency. So if
you borrow in silver דינרי, dinarei, you pay back in silver דינרי.
dinarei. Remember the concern is is that if it's not considered currency,
then it's like borrowing an egg and paying back an egg, and
its relative value might have changed relative to what we are considering
to be the actual way of defining prices. Okay, so if it's
silver clearly you can borrow in silver coin and pay back. אלא
פשיטא דינר דזהב בדינר דזהב. Ella peshita dinar dizahav bdinar dizahav. What
we mean is like we discussed yesterday, remember the case of the
guy who borrowed from רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiya daughter, right? And he
borrowed in gold דינרי. dinarei. Can I pay back? back in gold
דינרי dinari because if you consider the basic way of assessing value
based on silver, so if I borrowed a gold דינר dinar coin
and I paid it back, it might be worth a different silver
amount by the time I pay it back, and maybe it would
be ריבית. ribbis. So it sounds like that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is saying: you can't borrow gold and pay back gold, okay,
because it might be worth a different silver amount, which basically seems
to say that gold, even when taken by itself—I'm borrowing gold and
I'm paying back gold—gold is never really considered currency; it's always considered
produce. Okay, so אלא פשיטא דינר של זהב בדינר של זהב. Ela
peshita dinar shel zahav bedinar shel zahav. ולמאן, Uleman, according to whom
is he making this claim?
אילימא בית הלל, Elima Beis Hillel, המטבע הוה, hamatbeia havae, בית הלל
Beis Hillel says that gold even relative to silver counts as currency.
אלא לאו בית שמאי, Ela lav Beis Shammai, it must be according
to
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. ושמע מינה, Ushma mina, and you see that
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan must understand that according to בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, not only can you not go from silver to gold, you
can't even go from fruit to gold. That gold, even not relative
to other currency, gold taken on its own terms, is always considered
produce and is not considered to be, you know, a product or
whatever, and is not considered to be currency, and that's why you
can't borrow gold and pay back gold. Now, just before we continue,
I should say that תוספות Tosafos asks the obvious question: since when
is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan פוסק posken-ing a הלכה halacha according to
בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? Does he hold like בית שמאי? Beis Shammai?
So תוספות Tosafos says, well, מימי Mimi means אליבא דבית שמאי, aliba
deBeis Shammai, although it doesn't sound like that. The other thing תוספות
Tosafos says, which is important, is that ultimately this all ties back
to the different versions of our משנה. mishna. And if your version
of our משנה mishna is the way our version is, הזהב קונה
את הכסף, hazahav koneh es hakesef, which means, remember, gold is product
and therefore by taking the gold the other side owes the money,
that's our version of the משנה. mishna. So that could be saying,
and that's similar to this בית שמאי Beis Shammai idea. That's basically
saying gold is product and not currency, and maybe even on purely
its own terms, even not relative to silver, gold is always considered
to be product and not currency. So it's a way of interpreting
actually our משנה; mishna; it's not just a בית שמאי Beis Shammai
position. Okay, so here you see that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan seems
to be saying that you can't borrow gold דינרי dinari and pay
back in gold דינרי. dinari. Okay, so that seems a bit proof.
So הגמרא hagemara says, לעולם אימא לך, Le'olam eima lach, I could
claim to you רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who דאמר מחללין, de'amar mechalelin,
that actually you can go from fruit to gold and it is
considered currency for that purpose.
ושאני הלוואה כיון דלעניין מקח וממכר שויוה רבנן כפירי? Veshani halva'ah keivan
del'inyan mikach umimkar shaveiha rabanan kepeirei? But when it comes to borrowing
money, since when it comes to exchange, right, exchanging gold for silver,
the Rabbis considered it to be fruit relative to silver, that's our
משנה. mishna. So דאמרינן איהו ניהו דאוקיר וזיל, de'amrinan ihu nihu de'okeir
vezil, that when there's a change in relative value, we say it's
the gold that is changing the value, not the silver that is
changing the value. Okay, so that's what we said when you're buying
gold for silver or silver for gold, that gold is considered the
product relative to silver, you know, silver is considered the currency. Okay.
So לגבי הלוואה נמי פירא הוי. Legabei halva'ah nami peira havei. So
when it comes to borrowing money as well, we will say that
we will consider it as a type as fruit, meaning that you
know, here's the issue, right? You've got like three scenarios. You've got,
okay, you've
got—I've gotta get me a coin. This is where I could really
use some different colors. Okay, you've got your pile of gold, there's
30 pieces of gold for silver. Okay, I guess you have to
make a bigger pile because there's a lot of silver. Okay, you're
exchanging your gold for your silver here. Okay. All right. So that's
when you're exchanging it. Okay. So when you're exchanging it, that's our
משנה. mishna. So there we say that's considered to be פירות. peiros.
Okay, this is really the purchase thing. Then you've got your case
of your מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, where you've got your fruit—you see
it's got these things which makes them fruit. Okay. Okay. And then
you know, and here you've got your—and here you've got your gold.
Okay. So in that case we want to say, no, in that
case maybe everybody would say that you are, you know, you're transferring
the קדושה kedusha to there. Everybody would say that that's טבעא, tiva,
that that's coin. Okay. So the question is—so here it's relative to
silver. Here it's relative to fruit and you're transferring. When you now
borrow money, okay,
here,
you're borrowing money, right, and you're giving it over. Okay. And you're
giving it over. So which model should you use? Okay, should you
say that in this type of an exchange it's considered
to be פירות peiros because when we, you know, we sort of
say this is the product being purchased? So here too it's basically
type of thing like it's like borrowing פירות peiros and therefore you
have to worry about its relative value. And you understand the logic
to that: if I'm borrowing gold, well, if I'm thinking about, well,
if I wanted to pay back silver, if I wanted to exchange
it for silver, right, meaning the very fact that—the point being that
the very fact that when you do this, you think of silver
as the coin, means maybe that when you're borrowing the money, you're
thinking about it in terms of its silver value. Right, this might
reflect the fact that we consider if you know that you're buying...
if you buy gold based on the silver value, that when you
take gold you're thinking about it in terms of what is its
silver value. That's the way you determine its purchasing power. Okay, so
therefore maybe it would be a problem and therefore you can't borrow
gold and pay back gold because this defines that you're thinking about
it in terms of silver. Whereas maybe here, right, you can base,
you know, so, whereas this might be a separate case. This might
be a case where it's just about transferring the קדושה Kedushah and
you don't even have to think about anything, like it's not about
paying this back. It's about doing this as a one-time act and
maybe you don't have to think about this in terms of its
sort of market value in terms of silver. So anyway, those are
the three cases and what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that
the fact that here we treat it as פירות Peirot does not
determine the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni case. Here we might say since
here it works as פירות, Peirot, when you borrow money and pay
it back, we're also going to think about it as פירות Peirot
and that'll be problematic. But maybe the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni case
you can always go ahead and treat it as coin. Okay, so
it is interesting. If you actually ask me personally, I would have
put this more by the מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. I would have
said when it's a transaction that does not involve silver, we're always
going to treat it as coin. Only when you bring silver into
the transaction does it make you reassess its status as coin. So
the more natural thing would have been to go like this, right?
But what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that no, that maybe
since ultimately, and I don't know, it doesn't say why, I would
have naturally done that. Okay, so but the גמרא Gemara is saying
is
it all about the קדושה Kedushah is
it all about the right so that's what the גמרא Gemara is
basically sort of saying is that even though here there's no silver
in the transaction, this is all fundamentally commerce, right, and as I
said also there's a sense here of paying back, so ultimately there's
some sense of what is its value and how are you going
to assess its value and this really becomes the exception. So you
might be able to say that in these cases we're always going
to consider it to be, even by itself, we're going to consider
it to be פירות, Peirot, but that doesn't mean you can't use
it for מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money. Okay, so actually what winds
up being is מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is the exception. Right, in
commercial aspects it's פירות, Peirot, but in מעשר שני Maaser Sheni it's
still coin and you can still redeem it on מעשר שני. Maaser
Sheni. Let's just read that, I'm going to read that. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, לא לעולם אימא לך, Lo le’olam
eima lach, I will tell you, לא לעולם אימא לך לרבי יוחנן
דאמר מחללי. Lo le’olam eima lach le-Rabbi Yochanan de-amar mechallei.
No, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan actually would say maybe they actually can
work for a מעשר שני Maaser Sheni purpose, gold coins. ושאני הלוואה
דכיון דדמי למיקח וממכר שוויה רבנן כפירי, V’shani halva'ah de-keivan de-dami le-mikach
u-mimkar shav-yuh rabanan ke-pirei, since when you're exchanging gold for silver it's
treated like fruit, דאמרינן איהו ניהו דאוקיר וזיל, de-amrinan ihu nihu de-okir
v’zil,
it's the one that's changing the value, the gold relative to the
silver. So since we view gold as a thing that has fluctuating
value, and therefore לגבי הלוואה נמי legabei halva'ah nami when it comes
to a loan, we're going to say you can't do it in
terms of דינר בדינר dinar be-dinar because that is something that we
recognize as having fluctuating value. פירא הואי. Peira havay. Okay, so therefore
once we in one area commercially recognize it as פירות Peirot and
something that's value fluctuates, you can't borrow in gold דינרי dinarei because
you're borrowing in something whose value fluctuates. But even down here, even
though it's something whose value fluctuates, you know, whatever, it's enough of
a coin to do this. One minute, הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami
mistabra,
that also makes sense, but to see the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
as an exception. דכי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, De-ki ata Ravin
amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין Ravin came, he came in the name
of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אף על פי שאמרו אסור ללוות דינר
בדינר, Af al pi she-amru assur lilvot dinar be-dinar, again the same
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, even though you can't borrow in דינר dinar
which now we're presuming can only mean gold דינרי dinarei to pay
back in gold דינרי, dinarei, because it's a type of a fruit,
it's something of fluctuating value, אבל מחללין מעשר שני עליו, aval mechallelin
maaser sheni alav,
it's still a good enough coin to transfer מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
on it. שמע מינה. Shema mina. Okay, so that's a good proof.
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is an exception. You can hold, it can
work for מעשר שני Maaser Sheni even though you hold that in
commercial purposes, even within the context of הלוואה, halva'ah, even not relative
to an exchange with silver, it would be considered, you know, fruit
and not coin. Yes.
So two questions. So one is, so we're not, we could have
interpreted maybe means like דינר dinar of זהב zahab with the equivalent
amount of כסף kesef or whatever it is, you know, כסף kesef
for זהב, zahab, I mean not one דינר. dinar.
Yeah, yeah, no, then you wouldn't have used the same term, דינר
בדינר dinar be-dinar obviously means the same.
What's, whatever, but we wouldn't have the same problem with copper?
Yes, so you would. So but, so it is interesting because, you
know, it's true, like you would imagine that if poor people are
borrowing they're probably borrowing in maybe even denominations less than silver, right?
So presumably it would be the same issue. Can you borrow with
copper with copper? You know, that's, that is my understanding, that's certainly
my understanding. Again, because the גמרא, Gemara, you know, the גמרא Gemara
has these sort of different חשבונות, cheshbonot, you know, copper has the
benefit of being much more widespread used like the גמרא Gemara said
before. So is it possible that the גמרא Gemara would consider copper
to be an acceptable coinage for borrowing when gold is not? You
know what I mean? I'm in terms of defining, maybe. Right, I
know, it's a, that is a really good question, I don't know,
the גמרא Gemara sort of never goes back. It also goes back
to the earlier discussion, right, about the פרוטה Pruta and all these
different things for different statuses. תוספות Tosafot claims, תוספות's Tosafot way of
reading that is that everything is relative to its gold value. But
רש"י Rashi doesn't read that way. Can you actually
have... So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. שמע מינה,
Shema mina, תא שמע. Ta Shma.
So now we're going to try to prove again what is the
story with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and gold. הפורט סלע ממעות מעשר
שני. Haporeis sela mimaos Maaser Sheni.
You are exchanging a סלע sela for you know of מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni money. Now the grammar here's a little funny but I'm
going to tell you the way רש"י Rashi reads it. בית שמאי
אומרים בכל סלע מעות. Beis Shammai omrim bechol sela ma'os. You basically
exchange you know if you are basically what you're doing the way
it sounds like what you're doing is is that you're handing in
a סלע sela and you're getting מעות ma'os which is basically like
like copper coins. You're exchanging your silver for your copper. בכל סלע
מעות. Bechol sela ma'os. Okay. And also the word פורט poreit like
which means פרט prat like which means like to break it into
smaller denominations. That's what it sounds like. Okay. רש"י Rashi says and
תוספות Tosafos does not disagree that what it actually means is the
reverse. That you have all of your copper מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
coins and now you're about to take this trip to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and you don't want to שלעפ schlepp down these sackfuls of pennies.
So what you want to do is you want to get these
silver coins in exchange. So you're doing the reverse, okay? You're exchanging
your copper מעשר שני Maaser Sheni coins for silver coins. הפורט סלע
ממעות מעשר שני. Haporeis sela mimaos Maaser Sheni.
Now בית שמאי אומרים בכל הסלע מעות. Beis Shammai omrim bechol hasela
ma'os. Actually means בכל המעות סלעים. bechol hama'os sela'im. Okay. Which is
you have to exchange all of your copper coins. Okay. Or you're
have to you're allowed to. I'll get back to that.
ובית הלל אומרים בשקל כסף ובשקל מעות. U'Veis Hillel omrim beshekel kesef
uveshekel ma'os. No no no. You do a שקל shekel which is
half of a סלע, sela, one שקל shekel worth of silver and
one שקל shekel of a worth of you know of copper coins.
So you basically keep half of the amount in copper and you
can convert the rest of it. Now what is the issue here?
What's the reason for this debate? So רש"י Rashi says that the
reason is is that you'll come to ירושלים Yerushalayim when all you
have on you is silver coins which is what בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says, right? So בית שמאי Beis Shammai maybe is saying it's
מותר muttar to have silver coins because that's what you want to
do. You want to have all silver coins to make it less
to שלעפ. schlepp. Okay. But then you're going to come to ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, everybody's going to come with all their silver coins, everybody's going
to run to change their money, okay, for copper coins, okay. And
there's going to be like a run on the market and the
the exchange rate will change so you'll get much fewer copper coins
for your silver because everybody's trying to change money. And who loses
out in the end of that? Well I mean you lose out
that you don't buy as much food with it but מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni loses out. You know less מעשר שני Maaser Sheni produce
you know less was bought with the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money.
Okay. So therefore because of הפסד מעשר שני hefseid Maaser Sheni you
don't want there to be a run on the copper market when
you come. You want to have available cash. Now still you would
still think why half and half? Like tell me to keep as
much available cash as can cover me over for the first few
days, you know, why exactly half and half I don't know. But
anyway that's why בית הלל Beis Hillel says it. Now how about
בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? Is בית שמאי Beis Shammai saying you're allowed
to do everything in silver because that's what you want to do?
You would think so. Of course תוספות Tosafos says that then this
should be a case of קולי בית שמאי וחומרי בית הלל. kulei
Beis Shammai vechumrei Beis Hillel. בית שמאי Beis Shammai is giving you
more latitude than בית הלל. Beis Hillel. He's letting you do it
all. So תוספות Tosafos says it sounds like בית שמאי Beis Shammai
saying you have to do it all silver. What's the logic for
that? So the logic for that is and now I forgot the
logic.
Hold on let's see.
Oh no no the logic is the logic is is that that
you're going to lose out because you're going to have to pay
the exchange fee twice. If you keep half of it in copper
then you won't pay the exchange fee for copper. You'll take copper
from your hometown you'll use it and so on here you'll have
to exchange it in silver just to immediately exchange it back into
copper. So that actually is going to you know that'll cause מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni lose out because of your exchange fee.
So therefore בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says you do all of it into silver. So the question is
are you allowed to do all in silver you must do all
in silver?
Okay you do all in silver aren't you losing it?
Yes
that's the point you're losing the exchange fee twice when you change
it into silver and change it back out. So that's why בית
שמאי Beis Shammai is saying oh you're saying wait wait that would
be why he should not allow you to do it. One minute
one minute.
Hold on.
Oh you're right you're right you're right one minute hold on you're
right one minute.
Yeah he says you shouldn't do it in multiple stages you should
do it all at once because if you do it in multiple
stages you'll pay the fee multiple times but that still doesn't explain
why you can't do half and half. Okay so forget that Michael's
right. That actually would be a good reason for בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. No the second thing תוספות Tosafos says is is that he
doesn't want you to keep so much copper around because copper will
get moldy and therefore it'll it could it could you could incur
loss that way. All right so one way or another בית שמאי
Beis Shammai is saying that either you're allowed to or you must
do it all in silver let's go with תוספות Tosafos's explanation because
the copper could get moldy and בית הלל Beis Hillel says you're
either allowed to or you must do it half and half in
order that you have money readily available to spend and it doesn't
cause a run on the market. Okay.
Yeah,
because then בית שמאי Beit Shammai is saying you must do it
all in silver, according to that way of reading, so he's not
being lenient, he's demanding. Now, the fact that it coincides with what
you might have wanted to do, that's an interesting point. Okay, anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Anyway, that's their debate, so
but now how is that relevant for us? השתא לבית שמאי לגבי
פריטי מחללין Hashta l'Beit Shammai l'gabe priti mechalin עד. ad.
So now it's Michael's question from before. If you say that gold
is not coin, and you can't let's say borrow gold for gold,
how about copper? Is copper more of a reason to be coin
than gold or less? Right on the one hand it's much less,
it's much more trivial, on the other hand it's much more widespread.
So here's the argument. See Michael, I forgot, it was coming right
up in the גמרא. Gemara. Everybody, we don't care right now for
the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel בית שמאי Beit Shammai about
switching your copper coins for silver coins. What we care about is
that you started with copper coins, which means you transferred your מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni money, your מעשר שני Maaser Sheni fruit onto your
copper coins. So if you can transfer it onto copper coins, if
copper coins is considered to be coin for מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
purposes, certainly gold should be. Okay, so that's the argument. השתא לבית
שמאי לגבי פריטי מחללין, Hashta l'Beit Shammai l'gabe priti mechalin,
if when it comes to copper coins you can transfer the קדושה
kedusha of מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, לגבי דהבא מיבעיא, l'gabe dehav mibaya,
is it any different when it comes to—is there any question that
it should work for gold? Gold of course should be more of
a coin than copper. And here's the answer. No, שאני פריטי, shani
priti, no, פרוטות, perutot, copper coins are different, באתרא דסגין, b'asra d'sagyin,
in the place where they are sort of where they're current, where
they're you know where they're spread and they're used, חריפי, charifi, they
are they're more powerful, right? That that actually, it might be that
they don't work in other locales, but in the in the places
which accept them, they're actually more widespread and more currency than certainly
than gold, maybe even than silver. All right. So here it is,
exactly the question that Michael asked. It's possible that when it comes
to מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, gold is not considered currency and copper
is. How about when it comes to loans? What would be the
story about borrowing in copper and paying back in copper? That's a
good question. Yes.
It has to be less currency than silver because you can remove
the קדושה kedusha from there?
Or at least equivalent. Right. We haven't discussed that about equivalent to
equivalent in מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, we'll get to it a little
bit, but pos—you know quite possible. Right. Okay, so let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: All right, לשנא אחרינא,
lishna achrina, another way—so that way of saying the debate is, is
the—you know is gold considered currency relative to silver for transferring קדושה,
kedusha, or is—and is gold maybe even currency at all even when
it comes relative to fruit? That's one way of saying the debate.
לשנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another way of saying the debate of רבי
יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish is
אמרי לה amrei lah רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish
חד אמר מחלוקת בסלעים
על דינרים. chada amar machlokes b'sela'im al dinarim. The debate of בית
הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel v'Beit Shammai is silver to gold. בית
שמאי סברי הכסף כסף ראשון ולא כסף שני. Beit Shammai savri ha-kesef,
kesef rishon v'lo kesef sheni. It says וצרת הכסף בידך, v'tzarta ha-kesef
b'yadcha,
the money, the money means the only thing that is legitimate as
money of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is the first money, the money
that you transferred the קדושה kedusha to. You are not able—I don't
care gold to silver, silver to gold, silver to silver, gold whatever,
copper to silver, you are not allowed to transfer from the first
money to any second money. The only thing that can have קדושת
מעשר שני kedushas Maaser Sheni is the initial money that you did
the פדיון pidyon on. Could have been copper, could have been any.
Of course that's not going to work with the משנה Mishnah we
just taught, with the debate we just taught. So the גמרא Gemara
is going to get to it. This is obviously going to be
thrown out because we just taught about transferring your copper coins to
your silver coins. Okay. I know. So anyway, הכסף כסף ראשון ולא
כסף שני. ha-kesef, kesef rishon v'lo kesef sheni. You're only the first
money. בית הלל סברי Beit Hillel savri no, הכסף כסף ריבה. ha-kesef,
kesef riba. So no, it says הכסף ha-kesef and then says כסף,
kesef, it means any type of money, ואפילו כסף שני, va'afilu kesef
sheni, you can even go from the first money to the second.
אבל פירות על דינרים, aval peirot al dinarim, but when it comes
to fruit directly to דינרי, dinarei, דברי הכל מחללינן. divrei hakol mechalinan.
Everybody says you can. So according to that, the debate is not
about gold versus silver, it's just about can you transfer money to
money? So that's one version of the debate. לשנא אחרינא, lishna achrina,
another way of saying the debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rabbi
Yochanan v'Resh Lakish, is חד אמר דהתם ככסף ראשון הוא, chada amar
d'hasam k'kesef rishon hu, because then it's, you know, from פירות peirot
to gold, it's still the gold is still the first money. It's
not a question about what's coin, it's a question about coin to
coin. That's one of the רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh
Lakish opinions. וחד אמר בפירות על דינרים נמי מחלוקת. v'chada amar b'peirot
al dinarim nami machlokes. No, no, no, it's even a question about
going fruit to דינרי, dinarei, because it's not just about coin to
coin, it's a question whether gold דינרים dinarim are considered to be
coin all together. Okay, but at least one version now of reading
the debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel v'Beit Shammai is
not that gold is not coin, but that it's basically a categorical
statement that you can't go from coin to coin. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ולמאן דאמר סלעים על דינרים מחלוקת, u'l'man
d'amar sela'im al dinarim machlokes, one minute, according to that version that
the debate is only from silver to gold and because of, you
can never go from coin to coin, having nothing to do with
the issue of gold, according to that version, עד דמפלגי בסלעים על
דינרים לפלגי בסלעים על סלעים. ad d'mifligi b'sela'im al dinarim lifligi b'sela'im
al sela'im.
So then make it clearer that your issue is you can never
go from coin to coin. Don't talk about gold, which raises other
issues. Just say you're not allowed to go from silver to silver.
It would make it very clear that your issue here is about
coin to coin. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* of course says,
says why would anybody want to go from silver to silver? All
right. So maybe some of your silver is getting a little bit
rusty and whatever, who knows. There's some reason you might want. Anyway,
doesn't matter. Let's say you had... that's not our concern. אי פליגי
בסלעים על סלעים *Ei pligi bisla'im al sla'im*, if they had debated
silver to silver, how to show you that according to בית שמאי
Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* you can never go from coin to coin.
הוה אמינא הני מילי בסלעים על סלעים *Hava amina hani mili bisla'im
al sla'im* that that's where בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* disagreed
and he allows it because it's silver to silver. אבל בסלעים על
דינרים dinarim *Aval bisla'im al dinarim*, maybe if you would go from
silver to gold, maybe מודי ליה בית הלל Beit Hillel לבית שמאי
*modei leh Beis Hillel le'Beis Shammai*, maybe that case they would also,
they would say it's a problem. Not because you can't go from
coin to coin, but because of gold. דהוה ליה גבי כספא *de'hava
leh gabei caspa*, that gold relative to silver פירא הוי *pira hava*
is considered fruit. ולא מחללינן *ve'lo mechalelinan* and you can't do it.
קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan*, so to tell you the strength
of בית הלל Beit Hillel, *Beis Hillel*. בית הלל *Beis Hillel* lets
you go from silver to gold even though there are two potential
problems. One, it's coin to coin. And B, you might consider to
the of gold not to be coin relative to silver. Nevertheless, בית
הלל *Beis Hillel* allows it. But when בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis
Shammai* doesn't allow it, says this approach, it's not because of the
gold issue. It's because of the first issue that you can never
go from coin to coin. So now we're going to try to
disprove that.
I'm sorry, even silver to silver?
Even silver to silver.
According to בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai*. Like if you just
want smaller or like, you know, $10 silver?
Maybe. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* doesn't say that but maybe. Okay. So now
it goes what? That's what Michael said. Maybe there are different weights
of silver coins. But it doesn't sound like it. It sounds like
the one silver coin they had was silver דינרי *dinarei*. I don't
know. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this. Where are
we? קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan*. תא שמע Ta shma, *Ta
shema*. So now we're going to try to prove, is it possible
that בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* would hold you can never
go from coin to coin? הפורט סלע של מעשר שני בירושלים *Haporeis
sela shel Ma'aser Sheni bi'Yerushalayim*. Now we're talking finally about what the
word פורט *poreis* more naturally means. You're breaking it into smaller denominations.
You come to ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* and you have your silver coins,
and now you want to exchange them for your copper פרוטות *prutos*.
Okay. So so you're in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. בית שמאי אומרים בכל
הסלע מעות Beit Shammai omrim bechol hasela ma'ot, *Beis Shammai omrim be'chol
hasela ma'os*. So it's the same debate in reverse. בית שמאי Beit
Shammai. *Beis Shammai* says you basically either are allowed to or you
have to exchange, you know, all of your silver for, you know,
every silver coin for copper. ובית הלל אומרים בשקל כסף ובשקל מעות
u'Beit Hillel omrim beshekel kesef u'beshekel ma'ot. *U'Beis Hillel omrim be'shekel kesef
u've'shekel ma'os*. No, no, no. You take you can go ahead and
actually you're right because there are different types of silver. There's a
סלע *sela*, there's a שקל shekel, *shekel*. So you're right, there are
different sizes of silver coins. So maybe that's what the silver to
silver was. Bigger and smaller denominations. So I stand corrected. Okay. So
בית הלל *Beis Hillel* so anyway it's the parallel debate. בית שמאי
*Beis Shammai* says you break your entire silver, you know, you exchange
all your silver and בית הלל *Beis Hillel* says no, no, no,
only exchange half for the other used hold on to the other
half. So we're not going to worry now about what the issues
are, but they're similar to the issues before. Anyway, how is this
relevant for us? So what's relevant is that בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*
has you transferring your silver coins in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* for copper
coins. So that basically is going from כסף kesef לכסף *kesef le'kesef*.
So you see that בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* allows that. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, השתא כספא לגבי פרוטי מחללין *Hashta caspa
legabei pruti mechalelin*, here you see according to בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*
you can exchange your silver for your copper coins in ירושלים Yerushalayim,
*Yerushalayim*. ולא אמרינן כסף kesef ראשון ולא כסף שני *Ve'lo amrinan kesef
rishon ve'lo kesef sheini*. We don't say that the קדושה *kedusha* has
to only remain on the first money and not on second money.
So לגבי דהבא דחשיב מיניה מי אמרינן כסף ראשון ולא כסף שני
*Legabei dahava de'chashiv minei mi amrinan kesef rishon ve'lo kesef sheini*? Do
you think you would not be allowed to go from silver to
gold? Gold is obviously a more weighty, I mean it might okay,
you know, it's a more of a legitimate reason to transfer to
gold. It won't waste, it won't rust, it won't whatever. It's greater
value, it's more חשוב *chashuv*. So anyway, bottom line is, it's clear
here that בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* lets you go from silver to
copper. So how could anybody claim from בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* that
you can't go from money to money? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, so רבא *Rava* says, ירושלים Yerushalayim קא
מותבת *Yerushalayim ka movat*? You're asking about changing money in ירושלים Yerushalayim,
*Yerushalayim*? Changing money in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* is very different than transferring
the money to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. Once you're in
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, what are you supposed to do with the money?
Spend it. Buy food.
Spend it. Okay, now of course you say spend it on food.
But nevertheless, once you're in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, you're at the stage where
the money is now supposed to be used, right? So it's not
just abstract transferring of קדושה *kedusha*. It's now the experience of making
use of the money, expending the money. So therefore that gives you
a lot more latitude.
So so
שאני ירושלים דכתיב ונתתה הכסף בכל אשר תאוה נפשך בבקר ובצאן *Shani
Yerushalayim de'chsiv ve'nasata hakesef be'chol asher te'aveh nafshcha be'vakar u've'tzon*. Spend it
on anything. Now of course the funny thing is that תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* says it's not really anything, like חז"ל *Chazal* say you're not
allowed to spend it on like water or salt and things that
don't grow.
So but still here, okay, that's when that's your final products, like
here you have a, you do have a basic license to spend
it and the transferring is part of the process of spending. Now,
Michael does raise the good question which is, in ירושלים would you
be allowed to go from silver to gold because that's not the
natural arc of what allows you to spend the money. I don't
know the answer to that. But the point is you can't bring
a question from the exchange that happens in ירושלים.
So what about the previous one?
So that's what we're going to do. I mean, okay, you know,
the גמרא's Gemara. just like, you know, it said, no, no, no,
I'm thrilled that you're asking, I'm so sorry, I'm just saying it's
frustrating. I get it, it's like, you had the answer! You knew
it! But you know, that's only because like you have the advantage
of
foreknowledge. Right, this is a different version of the debate. So in
this version of the debate we didn't yet know the ברייתא baraita
that we quoted earlier. All right, so let's take a look. Anyway,
you know, the גמרא, Gemara I, to respond to your frustration, you
know, the גמרא Gemara sometimes knows the answer but likes to dole
out the information to develop the idea, even though it could jump
to the last point and shortcut, you know, make, you know, shortcut
the whole argument. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תא שמע, come and hear. הפורט סלע ממעות מעשר שני, Haporet sela
mema'ot ma'aser sheni, בית שמאי אומרים בכל הסלע מעות, ובית הלל אומרים
בשקל כסף ובשקל מעות. So here's changing your copper to silver outside
of ירושלים in order to make it easier to transfer. So there
you see, you're not in ירושלים and everybody says it's straightforward. You
can go from copper to silver. So how could anybody think that
you're not allowed, that there's a principle that you cannot go from
money to money? It's clear that בית הלל and בית שמאי agree
that there are cases you can do that. אלא, Ela, fine, so
throw that out. Okay, so
nobody takes the position you can't go from money to money.
אלא דכולי עלמא כסף כסף ריבה, Ela dechulei alma kesef kesef ribba,
you can go from money to money, אפילו כסף שני. afilu kesef
sheni. אלא אם דרבי יוחנן וריש לקיש הכי אתמר. Ela im d'Rabbi
Yochanan v'Resh Lakish hachi itmar. If there was another version of the
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, we
already had one version. One version of the debate is can you
go from fruit to gold? Right, that it's clear בית הלל and
בית שמאי debate can you go from silver to gold, and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish debate within בית שמאי
who doesn't like silver to gold but he allows fruit to gold.
That was our first version of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש. Resh Lakish. Here's our second version of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. אלא אם אתמר הכי אתמר. Ela im
itmar hachi itmar. חד אמר מחלוקת בשלונא על דינרין, Chad amar machloket
beshlona al dinarin, that the debate is when you go from silver
to gold. בית שמאי סבר, Beit Shammai savar, and now we're going
to bring a total different way of thinking about it. It is
not about gold not being coin. It is a completely different concern.
What's the concern? בית שמאי סברי גזרינן שמא ישהה עליותיו. Beit Shammai
savri gazrinan shema yish'a aliyotav.
Maybe you will wait to do the transfer because gold is very,
you know, it's a, there's a lot, you know, it's a big
denomination. So if you are going to allow me to transfer silver
to gold to bring my coins to ירושלים, I only have ten
silver coins, okay? So I'm going to say like, oh you know,
fine, I'll just wait till I get twenty-five and I won't bring
them to ירושלים this year, I'll wait till like next year to
do the transfer because I don't have enough silver to transfer to
gold. Now, it's a little funny concern of גזירה gezeirah because, you
know, if I have, meaning, if I have ten thousand silver, you
know, ten thousand and twelve silver, so you let me transfer the
first ten thousand. The only concern of where I might wait is
for that last denomination, that last coin. So who's going to stop
me from going to ירושלים, why would I not go to ירושלים
because I have to carry twelve silver coins in my pocket because
I don't have twenty-five to transfer to gold? We're not talking about
the whole amount, right? We're talking about the remainder. So I don't
really understand that. But anyway, that's how we're explaining it. That בית
שמאי's problem of silver to gold is not that gold is not
a coin but that it'll make you hesitate and wait till next
year before you do the transfer because you don't have enough silver
for the gold. Okay. דזימנין דלא מלו זוזי בדינרא. D'zimnin d'lo malu
zuzei b'dinara. Sometimes you will not have enough silver coins for the
gold ones, you know, to do the, it won't be a full
twenty-five. ולא מסיק, V'lo masik, and you won't take it up to
ירושלים this year, you'll wait till next year when you have enough
to do the transfer. ובית הלל סברי, U'Beit Hillel savri, בית הלל,
לא גזרינן שמא ישהה עליותיו, lo gazrinan shema yish'a aliyotav, we're not
afraid. דכי לא מלו נמי בדינרא אסוקי מסיק להו, D'chi lo malu
nami b'dinara asukei masik lehu, because even if you don't like, you
know, have enough to fill up a coin, you'll still take it
up because, you know, because like as I said, it's really just,
you know, look at רש"י. Rashi. דכי אסוקי מסיק להו שאין משאן
כבד שמעכב. D'chi asukei masik lehu she'ein masan kaved she'ma'akeh. So you
have, fine, you have twenty-four, worst case scenario you have twenty-four silver
coins. You'll take up everything else in gold דינרים and you'll take
up the remainder in silver coins, big deal, which is a pretty
good point and makes it hard to understand בית שמאי. Okay. דכי
לא מלו נמי בדינרא, D'chi lo malu nami b'dinara, even if you
don't have enough דינרא, dinara, you know, even if it doesn't fill
up a דינר, dinar, אסוקי מסיק להו, asukei masik lehu, so you'll
take the remainder in silver, big deal. אבל פירות על דינרים, Aval
peirot al dinarim,
anyway, according to that it's a גזירה gezeirah issue. But fundamentally gold
Gold is of course a coin. The whole issue was some גזירה
*gezeira*. Okay, that's a completely new way of reading it. And therefore,
since it's just a גזירה *gezeira* issue, okay, when it comes to
fruit on the דינרי *dinarei*, דברי הכל מחללינן *divrei hakol mechalelinan*. Everybody
agrees you can. Now why? If you allow me to do fruit
on gold דינרי *dinarei*, I get that gold דינרי *dinarei* is a
coin, but now I'm gonna wait, I'm not, you know, I'm not
gonna have enough fruit for one gold דינר dinar *dinar*, it'll also
make me wait.
Right, this is in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*?
No, out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, to transfer it.
Of course, that's the whole point. The reason why you're transferring it
to money is because, you know, I know.
But if I only have a tenth of a gold coin worth
of fruit, so I'm not gonna bother doing it, I'll say I'll
wait till next year when I can fill up the whole gold
coin. I'm not gonna go spend a whole gold coin for מעשר
שני *Ma'aser Sheni* money, why should I do it? I'll wait till
I fill it up and then I'll take it. So if I'm
afraid about waiting with the silver, I should be concerned about waiting
with the fruit. Right, wait, wait, you don't understand the question? I
understand. Okay, so let's see what the answer is, okay, because this
is all גזירה *gezeira*, gold is definitely considered coin. So אבל בפירות
על דינרים דברי הכל מחללינן *Aval bepeiros al dinarim divrei hakol mechalelinan*,
why? דכיון דמרקבי *dekeivan demarkevi*, because fruit rots. Okay, and you can't
eat the fruit with קדושת מעשר שני *kedushat Ma'aser Sheni* out of
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So therefore, you're, if you say I'll wait till next
year, you'll wait till next year and it'll all go to waste,
so you're not going to wait till next year. Okay, לא משהי
להו *lo mash'ei lehu*, you won't let it stay around. וחד אמר
*vechad amar*, that's one version of it. Gold is definitely a coin,
the question is a גזירה *gezeira*, and גזירה *gezeira* might be by
silver coins, but it won't be by fruit.
Right, this is all by the, they're only debating בית שמאי *Beis
Shamai*.
בית שמאי *Beis Shamai*, right. וחד אמר *vechad amar*, אפילו בפירות על
דינרים נמי מחלוקת *afilu bepeiros al dinarim nami machlokes*. No, that even
that if we're afraid presumably if we're afraid that you're going to
postpone till you have enough silver coins, we're also afraid you'll postpone
till you have enough fruit, and then actually it'll be even more
disastrous. Not disastrous, whatever, anyway, you know, more consequential because then the
fruit will rot and there'll be more loss. Okay, so this is
a version that everybody thinks gold is a coin and the whole
debate is whether we're concerned about that you'll wait till next year
because you won't have enough to transfer to the gold coin. You
had a question? No, I'm fine. Okay, you're good, Eli? Yeah? Okay,
good. Alright, so that's a new version of the debate. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. בשלמא להך לישנא דאמרת דמדאורייתא מישרי
שרי *bishlama lehach lishna de'amart demide'oraisa mishre sharei*, according to the version
that you just got through saying that everybody agrees that it works
from the תורה *Torah*, that you can, gold is a coin and
you can transfer onto it, ורבנן הוא דגזרו ביה *verabanan hu degazru
bei*, and the whole issue about using gold coins here with מעשר
שני *Ma'aser Sheni* is a rabbinic safeguard. היינו דקתני hainu dikatani יעשה
ולא יעשה *hainu deka'tani ya'ase velo ya'ase*. That's why the phrase of
the debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי *Beis Hillel veBeis Shamai* is
should you
make your, you know, your gold coins into מעשר שני *Ma'aser Sheni*
from your silver? So it's a לכתחילה *lechatchila* language, are you allowed
to do this? Can you make the gold-silver transfer? אלא להך לישנא
דאמרת דמדאורייתא פליגי *ela lehach lishna de'amart demide'oraisa peligi*, but if the
debate is whether it works according to the תורה *Torah*, whether gold
is considered a coin at least vis-a-vis silver, and if gold is
not considered a coin vis-a-vis silver, then the transfer won't work, right?
Because if it's not a coin, then you didn't transfer onto money.
So according to that, it shouldn't say should you do it, it
should say מחללין ולא מחללין מיבעי ליה *mechalelin velo mechalelin miba'ei lei*.
It should have said can it be done? Right, if you say
לא יעשה *lo ya'ase*, you should not do this, that would imply
that it's a לכתחילה *lechatchila* concern and בדיעבד *bedi'avad* it would work.
But if you would say אין מחללין *ein mechalelin*, it may not,
it cannot be transferred, it means that even בדיעבד *bedi'avad* it won't
work because this thing is not really considered to be a coin,
at least in this context. So anyway, so according to the first
version, we should have said it in that language. Katz, the version,
no, the language if you look back on מד עמוד ב *mem
dalet amud beis*, yeah, בית שמאי אומרים לא יעשה אדם סלעים דינרי
זהב *Beis Shamai omrim lo ya'ase adam sela'im dinarei zahav*. Okay, it's
משנה mishnah *Mishna* מעשר שני *Ma'aser Sheni*, right? It's not אין מחללין
*ein mechalelin* the סלעים *sela'im* on דינרי זהב *dinarei zahav*, but לא
יעשה *lo ya'ase*, you shouldn't. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קשיא
*kashya*, you're right, that's a good question. Okay, so anyway, there's different
ways of understanding this debate about בית הלל ובית שמאי *Beis Hillel
veBeis Shamai*. Is it just some גזירה *gezeira* and some safeguard around
מעשר שני *Ma'aser Sheni*, or is it a question about whether gold
is considered to be a coin at least vis-a-vis silver and then
vis-a-vis פירות peirot *peiros*? And that really is the big question right
from the beginning and actually this ends our first big סוגיא *sugya*.
So the first סוגיא *sugya* of הזהב קונה את הכסף hazahav koneh
et hakesef, והכסף אינו קונה koneh את הזהב *hazahav koneh es hakesef
vehakesef eino koneh es hazahav* is the question about is gold considered
to be coin or fruit vis-a-vis silver. There's two versions of the
משנה mishnah. *Mishna*, רבי *Rebbi* in his young age, רבי *Rebbi* in
his old age. Here we have a debate about בית הלל ובית
שמאי *Beis Hillel veBeis Shamai*. It obviously, you know, the גמרא *Gemara*
is biased very much according to our משנה mishnah, *Mishna*, seems to,
well actually that's not fair. The גמרא *Gemara* we just read today,
you know, seems to weigh in favor of our משנה mishnah *Mishna*
that silver is definitely coin, there's a question whether gold is coin.
The גמרא *Gemara* we said yesterday gave a whole list of אמוראים
*Amoraim* that felt that gold was a coin and maybe whether it
was more of a coin than silver, whatever, but maybe, maybe everything
is the gold standard. So we have these sort of two debating
issues and possibly and the two, so there's a question about מעשר
שני *Ma'aser Sheni* which might operate by its own terms, but the
two very relevant commerce issues are when you exchange... exchange them, which
one is the object, which one finalizes the deal because you took
the product as opposed to the payment of the product, and the
very interesting case of borrowing money. Is it possible that you could
borrow money in a particular currency and not be allowed to pay
back in the same currency because it's not considered a currency? Because
it's considered a currency of fluctuating value? Maybe that's also an easier
way of thinking about it, right? Which is considered to be the
stable currency and which are all the other currencies that are considered
to fluctuate their value relative to the stable one?
And when you borrow money, you have to pay back only in
terms of the stable currency, not in terms of a currency that
is seen of having fluctuating value. Yeah. And we would say that
today would apply, right? Like you know, if I borrow like dollar
bills, I can't pay you a gold, whatever it is, or silver
dollar, or whatever. You mean dollar for dollar? Yeah. If I borrow
one dollar bill, I can give you a silver dollar, whatever it
is. You mean dollar for dollar. Yes, but that's because in America
we only have one currency. If you were in a place, I'm
trying to think, is there any place in this that, I mean
I guess what would
happen if you were
in a European country and you borrowed in Euros or you borrowed
in the local currency? That would be really interesting question. Right? If
I borrowed in francs, could I pay back in francs, or do
we really think everything is in Euros?
I mean when people go to France, what is it? Francs don't
exist anymore.
Oh, it doesn't exist at all. Oh, so in all the countries
that adopt Euros, there's a,
but Britain never gave up the pound.
I mean I know there's Brexit, but they never gave up the
pound, right? But they also, yeah. If you're in England, you can't
buy things with pounds?
They don't, well, you can buy things with dollars. I mean here
you can buy things with whatever currency you want.
It's just not the official currency.
Yeah, but you'd have to go to like a money changer or
the storekeeper would...
No, like in
Canada for example or in border, you know, towns, there's lots of
stores that accept cross-border currency. Aha. But wait a minute. Are pounds
and francs no longer part of the currency exchange? They're no longer
seen as... No, I don't think so. Really?
It's just because they never went with the Euro. Aha. Okay. Interesting.
So שקלים, dollars, whatever? Yeah, anyway, if you could imagine a
country that actually had two side-by-side viable currencies, right? Then it would
be the interesting question. Which is considered the standard one? And which
is considered the one that has fluctuating value relative to the standard?
So oftentimes even in lots of countries where currency, you know, is
not stable, they'll take US dollars. Right. Right. So that would be,
yeah, so those would be interesting questions. All right. Let's now move
on to a new topic which is very, which is nice as
I, it's new, it's nice because it's a, you know, I really
like that last topic, but I think, you know, but it was
maybe getting a little confusing for people. I enjoyed that a lot.
Anyway, but this is also like a new nice conceptual topic and
it still deals with gold but in a very different way. Let's
take a look. Okay. איתמר Itmar was taught, רב ולוי, Rav v'Levi,
a debate of רב Rav and לוי. Levi. חד אמר מטבע נעשה
חליפין וחד אמר אין מטבע נעשה חליפין.
Chad amar matbeia naaseh chalipin
v'chad
amar ein matbeia naaseh chalipin. Can you use a coin to do
חליפין chalipin with? Now what that means is the following. You all,
I think you all know that there's something called a קנין סודר,
Kinyan Sudar, right? A קנין סודר Kinyan Sudar is like I give
you a handkerchief, you take it, and that finalizes the deal. Like
a פשיטא. pshita. Right, right. Now to some degree what that works
off of is a model of barter. You take my cow and
I get your donkey. So you take my handkerchief and I get
your cow. Now obviously when it's out of, when it's out of
proportion, it's a little funny to call it an exchange, but maybe
you could always conceptualize it as a type of a barter. But
that's not really true. Because there are cases where it's not based
on exchange at all. You think about what happens at the חתנ'ס
טיש, choson's tish, you know, at the signing of the כתובה, kesubah,
you know, you're the rabbi, you say, here, take my watch, you
know, and by taking my watch, I'm representing the כלה, kallah, you're
taking my watch and you're obligating yourself to me here with all
of the oblig- or to the כלה kallah with all the כתובה
kesubah obligations. Now give, now give me back my watch. Okay. So
now that is a type of a חליפין, chalipin, but that's חליפין
chalipin which basically means by doing this it's almost like a handshake,
it's like it finalizes the deal, and therefore it could be worth,
work by assuming obligations, but it's and not just by transferring and
exchanging objects. But it could also work by exchanging objects. That's why
you take my handkerchief and now I own your ten thousand acres.
It's not really an exchange. Okay. So there's like a model of
straight swapping, and then there's a model of the handkerchief, of the
חליפין, chalipin, and then there's some cases which maybe it's not exactly
clear where they fall. So it's, so you're saying that the קנין
kinyan is supposed to show it's a גמירת דעת? gemirat daat? That
is the מעשה קנין, maaseh kinyan, that it expresses the גמירת דעת,
gemirat daat, yes. Okay. But it's not through the, it's not about
the physical object as much. Okay. So anyway, that's the idea of
חליפין. chalipin. Now here's the question. I want to buy your, you
know, I want to buy your cow. We set the price at
a thousand dollars. Okay. The way we're going to do it is
I could give you my handkerchief and you take my handkerchief and
now I own your cow. But instead, I don't have my handkerchief
on me here, here, take my שקל, shekel and by you take
my שקל and then I own your cow. Now I'm not paying
you for it. Okay. It's, you're using it as just an object
to do a חליפין chalipin swap, like you would do a חליפין
chalipin swap with... with a handkerchief or with a cow for a
donkey. Can you do it? So the first question to ask is
now the question is sometimes you'll say wait, wait, how do I
know whether when you're giving me the money you're giving me in
payment where it doesn't work when it's used as כסף as מה
ma as payment as opposed to giving it me as חליפין. chalipin.
So I mean then obvious index to that is way of testing
that is is am I paying you the amount agreed upon or
not? Right if I'm not pay or no no well sometimes you
pay a down payment but it's still payment but nevertheless you know
sometimes you just have to look at context. Okay? So I don't
know the there will be cases that are gray, but sometimes it'll
be very clear from context that I am giving you this coin
not as a payment I'm not buying it with this money, we're
just using it as the way to effect the transfer by doing
a type of a חליפין. chalipin. You take the coin and I
own that. Can you do it? So the question is are there
any restrictions over what objects can be used in the חליפין chalipin
exchange. So there's going to be a debate later on between רב
נחמן Rav Nachman and רב ששת Rav Sheshet whether פירות can be
used for חליפין, chalipin, fruit. But fruit doesn't mean fruit, like you've
seen now, fruit really is a way of sort of saying of
a more abstract category. Fruit means anything that is not a כלי,
kli, that is not an instrument. Okay, something that is a כלי
kli that is like manufactured and that serves a function that everybody
agrees that's חליפין, chalipin, like the פסוק passuk the פסוק passuk in
רות, Ruth, שלף איש נעלו ונתן לרעהו, shalaf ish naalo venatan lereihu,
like taking off does that mean your shoe or your glove or
something but you know the idea yeah some say נעלו naalo can
mean a glove. Anyway, but but that is the classic paradigm of
חליפין, chalipin, not of the horse for the donkey, but the חליפין
chalipin of the handkerchief is giving your נעלו. naalo. So the question
is what about something that's not like a shoe? What about something
that's fruit? Okay, so that's a debate. So רש"י Rashi says here
okay, but let's assume it doesn't have to be a כלי. kli.
It can even be fruit. Can it be coin? Can you use
coin as the object of חליפין? chalipin? That is the question that
we're going to deal with right now. Okay? By the way, תוספות
suggests that maybe coin could even work even if you do require
a כלי, kli, because maybe money can is considered a type of
a כלי, kli, okay? Because first of all you use money to
do things with, to buy things with and so on. Anyway, that's
an interesting debate. But we're going to see about the debate of
כלי kli versus fruit. Now we want to know even if you
generally are of a very expansive view of the objects you can
use for חליפין, chalipin, how about coin? Is coin always different? Coin
is always like currency, it's never an object. Okay? So that's the
question. Let's take a look. איתמר, Itmar, it was said. רב ולוי,
Rav veLevi, חד אמר מטבע נעשה חליפין, chad amar matbe'a na'aseh chalipin,
you can use a coin for חליפין chalipin וחד אמר אין מטבע
נעשה חליפין, vechad amar ein matbe'a na'aseh chalipin, you cannot. אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר אין מטבע נעשה חליפין?
mai ta'ama deman de'amar ein matbe'a na'aseh chalipin? Right? Why should you
exclude it if you have a broad category of things you can
use, why should coin be excluded? משום דדעתיה אצורתא, mishum de'daatei atzurata,
because your intent is on the is on the image, on the
you know sort of the stamped image, וצורתא עבידא דבטלה, vetzurata avida
dabatela, and sometimes that is nullified. What does this mean? So רש"י
Rashi says what it means is is that the reason you're sort
of giving value to the coin is not because if you focus
just on the precious metal, if I gave you a slug, if
I gave you a round piece of gold that had not been
stamped, of course we could use it for חליפין. chalipin. I mean
if you could use fruit, you could use metal. Right? I'm giving
you metal, you take a piece of metal and now we've done
the חליפין. chalipin. But a coin is not conceptualized even if it
does have intrinsic value in terms of the metal. It's conceptualized in
terms of the buying power. Now the way he says it is
you think about the stamp. What? What is he saying? He's saying
this currency can be invalidated. Yes, and that was the גמרא. So
because about its its role as currency, well sometimes you know the
government you know invalidates certain currencies and says they're no longer they're
no longer usable. And therefore it's not a strong enough object. Now
I don't I gotta tell you I really don't understand that because
like and let's say I give you I don't know something that's
easily breakable, right? I give you something that you know can snap
in a second and easily break. Well it's a disposable thing, it's
a trivial thing, it's going to easily break. I I bet you
there are a million objects that would more easily break than the
likelihood that the currency is going to be nullified by the government.
Okay especially depending on what currency you give. I I'm more inclined
to think that what it means is is that it's sort of
like you know you know how the גמרא sort of says like
sometimes a שטר shtar is not included because it doesn't have intrinsic
value. So a coin has intrinsic value, but you don't relate to
it in terms of its intrinsic value, you relate to it in
terms of its more abstract buying power. And therefore it's less of
an object than a fruit or a pencil. You know, even you
might not need a כלי, kli, you might have a fruit, but
whether it's a fruit or a pencil or anything or watch or
an iPhone, all those things you sort of relate to in terms
of their like because they directly can be used, whereas coin is
more about what it represents than about what it can be used.
That's how I would I read it but I I struggle to
understand exactly what the problem here is. Okay anyway. So now the
face coin be value. Ironically a defaced coin, if you say that
you can use fruit, then you should be able to use a
defaced coin, because then you're just transferring an object of value, just
transferring metal, using a piece of metal. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like this. Anyway, so that's the debate, whether you can use
a coin for חליפין. Chalipin. Okay, תנן. tenan. ותנן הזהב קונה את
הכסף. v'tenan hazahav koneh et hakesef. So now we're going to get
to our משנה Mishna where you take possession of the gold and
the other person now and you owe the person the silver. Now,
מאי לאו, mai lav, now we think it does not mean that
I am buying gold for silver, but we think it means I
take gold and in exchange you own the pile of silver in
my house. You understand the difference? Do I owe you the amount
we agreed upon or do you own the silver in my house?
And the גמרא'ס Gemara's focus is on the word קונה את הכסף.
koneh et hakesef. קונה את הכסף Koneh et hakesef does not sound
like I agree to pay you now I owe you the money,
it sounds like I took gold and in exchange you own that
pile of silver in my house. Does that sound like a חליפין
Chalipin case? Okay, מאי לאו דחליפין? mai lav dechalipin? It sounds like
you're doing חליפין. Chalipin. ושמע מינה מטבע נעשה חליפין. ushma mina matbeia
na'aseh chalipin. You can use a coin for חליפין. Chalipin. לא, בדמים.
lo, bedamim. No, it doesn't mean that you own the pile of
silver, it means you owe the guy the money. אי הכי, ei
hachi, if that's true, הזהב קונה את הכסף, hazahav koneh et hakesef.
it shouldn't say that taking possession of the gold makes the person
own the silver, it should have said מחייב מיבעי ליה. mechayev mibaei
lei. Taking possession of the gold makes you obligated to pay the
amount agreed upon, pay the silver. Okay, תני הזהב מחייב. tani hazahav
mechayev. Fine, switch the gears. תוספות says we're not really switching the
gears, so what we're really just saying is that's what the word
means. Okay, קונה koneh, here does not mean literally you own a
pile of silver, it means now the other side owes you the
silver agreed upon. הכי נמי מסתברא. hachi nami mistabra. You know what?
It makes sense that here we're talking not about חליפין Chalipin and
we're talking actually about owing the money, מדקתני סיפא הכסף אינו קונה
את הזהב. midekatni seifa hakesef eino koneh et hazahav. If you take
the silver, that doesn't work for to owe the gold. אי אמרת
בשלמא בדמים, ei amrat bishlama bedamim, if we're talking about paying for
it, so היינו דאמרינן דהבא פירא וכספא טיבעא. hainu de'amrinan dahava peira
vechaspa tiv'a. So that's how we've been explaining it until now, that
gold is considered to be fruit and silver is considered to be
the payment, the coin. וטיבעא פירא לא קני. vetiv'a peira lo kani.
When you take payment, you take the silver, taking payment doesn't make
the other side own the product, right? You have to take the
product, not take the payment. That's how we've explained the משנה. Mishna
Everybody get that? If it's about buying the thing and it's about
payment for it, so silver is payment, gold is not payment. Okay,
I mean, or I should say it the other way: gold is
the object, silver is not the object, and you have to take
possession of the object. אלא אי אמרת בחליפין, ella ei amrat bechalipin,
but if what we're talking about is a pile of gold and
a pile of silver, and we're talking about חליפין, Chalipin, not about
a payment but about swapping, okay, and we're saying you can swap
by, you can use coin for swapping, you just can't use them,
it's you know, that's the issue. אלא אי אמרת בחליפין, ella ei
amrat bechalipin, תרוייהו ליקנו אהדדי. travayhu liknu ahadadi. So then you should
be able to take a gold, you should be able to swap
gold for silver and silver for gold, right? If you're saying the
issue is, it's an issue of payment of the money and you
have to take the product and it's the taking the product that
finalizes the deal, not taking the payment, then you can say silver
is payment, gold is product. That makes sense. But if what you're
telling me is you can do חליפין Chalipin with coins, coins are
okay for חליפין, Chalipin, and we're talking about two different piles of
gold and of silver, then it shouldn't matter which one you to
take, right? Take the gold, take the silver, you did a חליפין
Chalipin with a coin, and therefore the other side owns the other,
owes, owns the other pile of coins. Okay, so if it's all
about חליפין Chalipin with coins, then there should be no difference of
gold and silver. If it's about payment for an object, one could
be the object, one could be the payment. All right, so there's
no way to explain this משנה, Mishna that this משנה Mishna is
dealing with payment, it is not dealing with חליפין; Chalipin; if it
was חליפין Chalipin and you could do חליפין Chalipin with coins, it
would work whether with gold or with silver. Let's just read one
more line. ותניא, vetanya, we also learned a ברייתא: braita: הכסף אינו
קונה את הזהב. hakesef eino koneh et hazahav. Silver does not buy
silver? Gold. Thank you. כיצד, keitzad, מכר לו עשרים וחמשה דינר של
כסף בדינר של זהב.
machar lo esrim
vechamishah dinar
shel kesef bedinar shel zahav. You sold twenty-five silver דינר dinar for
one gold. אף על פי שמשך את הכסף, af al pi shemashach
et hakesef, even though one side took, you know, did the משיכה
meshichah on the silver, לא קנה עד שימשוך את הזהב. lo kanah
ad sheyimshoch et hazahav. The sale is not final until the gold
is taken, because the gold, remember, is the product, the silver is
the payment, the gold is the product. אי אמרת בשלמא בדמים, ei
amrat bishlama bedamim, if we're talking about payment for a product, משום
הכי לא קני, mishum hachi lo kani, that's why it didn't work
because silver is payment and payment does not effect the קניין, kinyan,
only taking the product does. אלא אי אמרת בחליפין, ella ei amrat
bechalipin, but if we're talking about doing it as a swap, ליקני.
likni.
So, ליקני, likni, so you took a piece of silver, let's effect
the swap.
You're saying that you can use a coin for doing חליפין. Chalipin.
So the גמרא says אלא מאי, ella mai, so what do you
want to say? בדמים? bedamim? That we're talking about payment? אי הכי
אימא רישא, ei hachi eima reisha, let's look at the beginning. הזהב
קונה koneh את הכסף. It can work with gold. כיצד? keitzad? מכר
לו דינר של זהב בעשרים וחמשה דינר של כסף. machar lo dinar
shel zahav be'esrim vechamishah dinar shel kesef. One דינר dinar. of gold
for twenty-five silver דינר. כיון שמשך את הזהב, keivan shemashach et hazahav,
נקנה הכסף בכל מקום שהוא. niknah hakesef bechol makom shehu. Once you
take the piece of gold, then the guy owns the silver wherever
it is. So so far this is consistent: gold is the product,
you take the gold. Gold, the other side owns the silver. Owns
or owes, well we'll see, the silver. So what is why is
this a challenge? This seems completely consistent with how we've understood the
משנה that it is about what is the product and what is
the payment. Because here's the problem. The problem is the language בכל
מקום שהוא. bechol makom shehu. The guy owns the silver wherever it
is. It sounds like it's not that now you're obligated to pay,
it sounds like it was a swap and he owns the silver
in
your house and
you're a שומר shomer now on my silver and if something goes
wrong, you have you know it's a question if you were פושע.
poshea. It sounds like it was a swap and not a purchase.
Okay, so the גמרא says where was it? אי אמרת בשלמא בחליפין,
Ei amart bishlama bachallifin, if we're talking about a swap, היינו hainu
דקתני נקנה הכסף בכל מקום שהוא. nikna hakesef bechol makom shehu. Now
the other side owns the silver wherever it is because you swapped,
it wasn't a sale it was a swap. אלא אי אמרת בדמים,
Ella ei amart bedamim, but if you say we're talking about payment
of money and owing the payment, היינו נקנה הכסף בכל מקום שהוא,
nikna hakesef bechol makom shehu, it shouldn't say the כסף is possessed
wherever it is, is owned. נתחייב גברא מיבעי ליה. Nitchayev gavra miba'ei
lei. It should say the other side now has to pay. Right?
The fact that it says you own the money makes it sound
like we're dealing with a swap. So אמר רב אשי Amar Rav
Ashi לעולם בדמים. le'olam bedamim. No no no we are talking about
owing the money ומהי umai בכל מקום שהוא, bechol makom shehu, this
is going to be a really forced reading. What does it mean
that you own the silver wherever it is? כמות שהוא. kemot shehu.
כדאמר ליה. kidi'amar lei. It means you are owed the silver as
according to the agreement בכל מקום, bechol makom, like right מכל מקום
mikol makom or according to how it was agreed. אי אמר ליה
Ei amar lei מאנקי חדתא יהבינא לך. me'anki chadta yahavina lach. The
guy says I'll pay you silver from a new wallet, meaning freshly
minted coins, לא מטי יהיב ליה lo mati yehav lei מאנקי עתיקא.
me'anki atika. He can't give him old coins, he has to do
what was agreed. אע"ג דעדיפי מיניה, af al gav di'adifi minei, even
though old coins are better, I guess they're better because I don't
know they show they've been used or something. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
דאמר ליה de'amar lei לציירן קא בעינא להו. letzayran ka ba'ina lehu.
No, I want new coins because I expect to keep them around
for a long time and therefore I want them fresh because it's
going to because I don't want them to I don't know get
moldy or something. Anyway, bottom line is is that the גמרא is
pointing out that the משנה speaks about קונה, which sounds like you're
dealing with a swap. And it sounds therefore that you can use
money for a swap, but if that were true we wouldn't be
able to explain the difference between why it works with you know
the difference between gold and silver. But there's definitely the word קונה
sounds like a swap and certainly קונה בכל מקום שהוא koneh bechol
makom shehu sounds like a swap, and but we are rejecting that
read because then we couldn't explain why it would matter whether it's
gold or silver. If you can use a coin for חליפין, challifin,
it should work either way. And therefore what we are saying is
the משנה and the ברייתא Braita talk about not a swap but
a sale, and therefore you do a קנין kinyan on the product.
The product is the gold, and then when you do that the
other side doesn't own the money, the other side is owed the
money. Okay, and that's how we're choosing to read our משנה and
this ברייתא, Braita, that it's a sale, it only works when you
focus on the product, the product is the gold, and then when
you do that the other side is owed the amount not not
owns the amount. So we'll continue tomorrow to look at this issue
about the gold and the silver okay and about I'm sorry about
about whether you can use a coin to do the act of
חליפין. challifin. All right, so we'll pick up here.